hello today i'm gonna be explaining to
you code ql query
for finding the dub injection that was
reported to github security lab on
hacker one and was rewarded
three thousand dollars first let's
explain
what is github security lab because it's
not standard github's back bounty
program
it's actually an initiative by github
that allows security researchers
to write code qr queries that find
actual vulnerabilities
in open source software now you're
probably wondering
what is called ql so let me briefly
explain it
it's the code analysis platform used by
security researchers to automate variant
analysis
it is not a simple static code analysis
performed by a simple text parsing
nor it's a dynamic analysis codeql does
not
actually run the application to submit
payloads it performs a semantic analysis
which means it actually understands what
the code does
how does the flow look and most
importantly from the security point of
view
which variables may contain user input
so the idea behind the github security
lab is
that there is public repository with all
the codeql queries
submitted by researchers that find
a lot of types of vulnerabilities and
everyone
can for free run those queries on their
applications
and find any bugs very early and the
researchers here
do not get paid for the vulnerabilities
they find
but for the queries they submit and the
bounty award is determined
based on the following factors the
complexity
severity and prevalence of the
vulnerability
as well as the performance and
documentation of the query you submit
so if you write such a query it's good
idea to first
run it on some open source applications
just to see whether it's reliable or not
and if those applications have bug
bounty programs
you will get a few payouts for a job
done once
because github's team will be very keen
to see
that your query actually finds
vulnerabilities
okay so now we have github security lab
and codeql explained
and we can start getting into this very
vulnerability
so now it's time to explain what is ldap
the acronym stands for lightweight
directory access protocol
and it's used for accessing and
maintaining distributed directory
information services
in simple words is used to access the
same file system
from a few computers connected by the
internet
the very typical query that would
validate
the credentials provided by the user
would look like this
it uses the notation where operands
follow the operator
so here first we have the end sign and
then we have two expressions
that both must be evaluated to true for
the whole expression to be evaluated to
true
and the concept behind ldap injection is
very similar to sql injection
we have our user input unfiltered and
put
into the query so we can escape the
context
and make the expression always return
true in this case
so such payload would be equivalent to
the typical sql injection
performed in the login bundle let's now
get to the actual
code qr queries the goal is to find
any methods that execute dub queries
on unfiltered user inputs this single
query
can detect the tab injection in plain
java gndi
unbound id sprinkled up and a patch ldap
api
this four of the seven files that we
have
in this part of the repository are just
examples of
well-written parts of the code executing
ldap queries
using these four technologies one more
file contains some help
so remaining two files are actually
written in the codeql language
so the first file is very short it looks
a bit like a sql query and it's meant to
be this way
because codeql is advertised that
it can work with the code as easy as
with the data
so for example such basic query would
fetch all variables
of type int from the analyzed code
so here source and sync are two points
of the flow of the application
and we want to check whether we can get
from one point
to another meeting at the same time our
requirements
stored in a conf variable that has the
type
defined by us and the select part
is just what will be returned if the
application
will be vulnerable so let's get into the
second file
it has 400 lines and i will try to just
briefly explain what's going on here
otherwise it would be a very long video
in simple words our sync has to be a
method that executes a ldap query and
source
has to be something with user input this
part of the code
validates that the method that we are
currently in
is one of three methods in unbound id
that
are vulnerable that is they execute ldap
query
and here in the spring part of the code
we have a bit of logic because there are
more functions
more parameters not all of them can be
our sinks
so we have to put some ifs here and
there but it's
not a very complicated code and big part
of the code here
just makes sure that we catch equivalent
calls that is if we call our method
on string it is equivalent if we create
a object of ldap name class using the
same string
as well as if we would create a new dab
name
and then use the method to string the
researcher
had to write code to catch all of these
variants so that's the brief logic
behind this called ql queries big kudos
from me to the researcher gregor
that actually wrote those queries and
got three thousand dollars from github
security lab
i think that's a cool way of doing
something great for community
and having a profit from it as well so
that's it for today's video
as always i will put relevant links like
the report
the comments and the researcher's
profile in the description
leave a like and a subscription if you
enjoyed the video
for now goodbye